Guide to the Thomas Anthony Thacher Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Thomas Anthony Thacher papers
1708-1886
MS 1697
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.25
The papers consist of correspondence, legal and financial documents, minutes of meetings, and memorabilia related to Thomas Anthony Thacher's personal life and family, his academic career at Yale College, and his interest in public higher education. Other papers in the collection consist of correspondence, legal and financial documents, church records, and a family tree that are related to other Thacher family members.
Thacher, Thomas Anthony, 1815-1886
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, ca. 1970. Gift from Anne Day Thacher, 2003.
Biographical / Historical
Thomas Anthony Thacher was born in Hartford, Connecticut on January 11, 1815. He received a B.A. degree from Yale College in 1835 and his M.A. degree in 1838. From 1838 to 1842, Thacher was a tutor at Yale College. He then advanced to assistant professor of Latin and Greek Languages from 1842 to 1845, assistant professor of Latin Language and Literature from 1845 to 1851, and professor of Latin Language and Literature from 1851 until his death on April 7, 1886. In addition to his teaching duties, Thacher was actively involved in the general administration of Yale College, particularly in the area of fund raising. He also served as a member of the Connecticut State Board of Education from its inception in 1865 until his resignation in 1877. Thacher received the degree of Doctor of Laws from Western Reserve College in 1869.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, legal and financial documents, minutes of meetings, and memorabilia related to Thomas Anthony Thacher's personal life, academic career at Yale College, and interest in public higher education. The records document Thacher's relationships with his family members as well as the development of his professional life from student to faculty member at Yale College. Folders are arranged alphabetically within headings. Correspondence is arranged both by individual and topic; much of this correspondence is personal, such as with Yale classmate Daniel Webster, sisters Apphia, Elizabeth, Lucy and Nancy, or his first wife, Elizabeth Day Thacher, and second wife, Elizabeth Sherman Thacher. Other correspondence and additional documents such as a grade book and minutes of meetings, relate to Thomas Thacher's academic career as a professor at Yale College. Various deeds, bills, and insurance documents pertain to his personal financial and legal obligations.
Additional records in the collection are related to other Thacher family members, especially Peter Thacher, the father of Thomas Thacher. These papers include correspondence, legal and financial documents, church records, and a family tree.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Education, Higher; Thacher, Thomas Anthony, 1815-1886; Yale University -- Administration; Yale University -- Finance
- Thacher, Thomas Anthony
  - Association of Officers of Colleges in New England [minutes of proceedings; Thacher was secretary for the first meeting], 1858-1860 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence
    - General, incoming [mainly professional], 1830-1885, undated (Box 1, Folder 2 - 4)
    - General, outgoing, 1836, 1843-1845 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Butler, Daniel, 1851-1884 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Day, Jeremiah [regarding appointment as tutor in Latin at Yale College], 1837-1846 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Day, Thomas [pertaining to Thomas Thacher's intention to write a biography of Jeremiah Day and Thomas Day], 1841-1854 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Kingsley, J. L. [correspondence while in Germany], 1843-1845 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Pratt, Julius H. [regarding taxes and sale of plots in Arlington Cemetery, New Jersey], 1882-1886 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Seymour, J. F., 1836-1858 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Stanley, T. [regarding post-college plans], 1836-1838 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Swayze, Wager, 1852-1885 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Thacher, Apphia, Elizabeth, Lucy, and Nancy (sisters) [housed in notebook], 1832-1851 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Thacher, Elizabeth (sister) [housed in notebook], 1831-1857 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Thacher, Elizabeth Day (first wife), 1846-1857 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Thacher, Elizabeth Sherman (second wife), 1840-1884 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Woolsey, Theodore Dwight (president of Yale College), 1845-1881, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Yale College fundraising, 1851-1886 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Deeds, wills and financial documents, 1708-1877 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Financial documents related to estates of Apphia Thacher, Elizabeth Thacher, Emmeline Thacher, Nancy Thacher (sisters), 1858-1874 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Fire and life insurance contracts and invoices, 1841-1877 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Grade book for Latin course, junior class, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Journal, 1884 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Lock of hair, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Notebook with reproductions of family letters and writings, 1886 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Power of attorney paper, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Thomas Anthony Thacher: Remarks Made at the Funeral Services by Professor Timothy Dwight, [1886] (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Yale Club of Cincinnati [memorial tribute], 1886 April 9 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Other Thacher family members
  - Parkes and Day family tree, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Thacher, Peter [correspondence with John Thacher, father, James and John Thacher, brothers, Anne Parkes, future wife, and others], 1793-1825 (Box 3, Folder 31 - 34)
  - Thacher, Peter [deeds], 1773-1847 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1718-1885 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Miscellaneous legal documents [power of attorney papers for the Dodd and Sprague families; Irene Larned's will; Timothy Wright's deed], 1849, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous religious writings, church records, and financial documents [mounted on heavy paper; mainly reproductions of 18th and 17th century documents], 1719-1758, undated (Box 4, Folder 38)